谢尔顿  有件事情我一直想跟你谈谈
So Sheldon, there's something I've been wanting to talk about
但我知道这话题有些敏感
but I know it's kind of a touchy subject.
成功把范围缩小到了任何事
Way to narrow it down to everything.
什么事
What is it?
你的生日就快到了
Well, your birthday's coming up.
而你从来不让我们帮你庆祝
And you've never let us celebrate it.
我在想  或许今年可以帮你庆祝一下
And I was hoping maybe this year we could.
我想这话题我们可以讨论
Oh, I suppose that's a discussion we could have.
那太好了  我觉得呢
Okay, great, I mean,
也不见得一定得是盛大的派对之类的
it doesn't have to be a big party or anything.
我只是...
I was just...
他上哪去了
Where'd he go?
等等
W-Wait a minute.
你一提到他的生日  他就落跑了吗
You mention his birthday and he vanishes?
这资讯这些年来都"躲哪去"了啊
Well, where's that information been this whole time?
他上哪了
Well, where is he?
谢尔顿
Sheldon?
我去看看他房间
I'll check his room.
惊喜
Surprise!
妈呀
Oh, my God!
这只是其中一个
Just one example
生日能怎么恶心你的例子
of how birthdays can be terrible.
我们现在可以放下这事
Now, can we please drop this subject
重新选个话题了吗
and pick a new one?
我提议聊聊  汤变成炖汤前
Yeah, I suggest how thick can a soup get
所能达到的最高浓稠度是多少
before it becomes a stew?
相信我  答案可能会让你很惊讶哟
You know, the answer, it may surprise you.
抱歉我提起这事
I'm sorry I brought it up.
问题到底在哪
Yeah, what is the problem?
是因为越来越老吗
Is it about getting older?
拜托  你看我陶瓷般光滑的肌肤
Please, look at this porcelain skin.
我简直就是人形洗手台
I'm like a human sink.
但这是一年中  全世界绕着你转的一天呢
But it's the one day a year that's just all about you.
就一天吗
One day.
呵呵
Ha ha.
对对对
Right.
求你就告诉我原因吧
Can you please just tell me why?
好吧
Fine.
你也知道  我有一个双胞胎妹妹
As you know, I have a twin sister
不用想也知道我们分享着同一个生日
with whom I obviously share a birthday.
每年我们都会办一个派对
Every year we'd have a party.
但我邀请的所有人都不会来
No one I invited would ever come,
因为他们不喜欢我
because they didn't like me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
这部分没多糟
Oh, that part wasn't so bad.
因为我也不喜欢他们
I didn't like them, either.
但在那天我永远也躲不过
But then I'd inevitably spend the whole day
我妹妹的朋友折磨的命运
being tortured by my sister's friends.
你个可怜的小家伙
Oh, you poor thing.
我六岁那年  他们说蝙蝠侠要来我的派对
When I was six, they told me Batman was coming to my party.
我在门口等了无数小时
I waited by the door for hours.
我看到最接近蝙蝠侠的事物
Closest thing to Batman I saw
是一只知更鸟[罗宾]撞到窗户
was when a robin flew into the window.
你知道那些事情现在不会再发生了吧
You realize none of those things would happen now?
我知道啊  但你干嘛在意
I do, but why do you care
我要不要庆祝我生日啊
if I celebrate my birthday at all?
你给了我上次生日留下那么难忘的回忆
Well, you made my last birthday so memorable,
我想报答你
I wanted to return the favor.
如果你现在举办派对
Yeah, if you had a party now,
你有许多会乐意来参加的朋友呢
you have plenty of friends that would love to come.
而我们就住在这  想不来都不行呢
And we live here, so we have no choice.
对啊
Yeah.
那好吧
Very well.
朕就恩准你们  通过举办有蛋糕  礼物
You may celebrate my life by throwing a party
无尽对我赞美爱慕的派对  来庆祝我的诞辰
with cake, presents and a shower of admiration and love.
但这事你可欠我一个大人情
But then you owe me big-time.
谢尔顿的首次生日派对
You have any idea what you're getting
你想到送什么礼物了吗
Sheldon for his birthday?
他最近很迷恐龙
He's been fascinated with dinosaurs lately.
或许我们能给他搞个化石
Maybe we could get him a fossil.
别给他侏罗纪时期的化石
Well, just don't get anything Jurassic.
他觉得那整段时期已经被好莱坞化了
He feels like that whole chunk of time has gone Hollywood.
对了  我想到
dort dort dort Hey, uh, you know,
他说了一件悲惨往事
he told a sad story about how his sister
当年他妹骗他蝙蝠侠会来参加他的派对
tricked him into thinking Batman was coming to his party.
这招有意思
That's funny.
咱们也来用一次
Let's do that.
或许我们可以让蝙蝠侠真的来参加
Maybe we could get Batman to actually show up.
你是说穿着白痴变装服的人吗
You mean, some guy in a lame suit?
或者是真的蝙蝠侠  斯图尔特
Or a real Batman. Hey, Stuart?
你不是有一次想找亚当·韦斯特来办签名会吗
Didn't you try to get Adam West to do a signing here once?
是啊  当时在日程安排上有些冲突
Yeah, but there was kind of a scheduling conflict.
他想知道哪一天能收到钱
He, uh, wanted to know when he'd get paid.
而我不愿意告诉他
And I wouldn't tell him.
能给我他的联系方式吗
Can I get his contact info?
行啊  但我先警告你
Sure, uh, but just so you know,
这人就是一事儿精
he's kind of a diva.
-是吗  -要了亲命
- He is? - Oh, yeah.
不愿意搭乘巴士
Won't take the bus.
不愿意自己准备午餐
He won't pack his own lunch.
不愿意让你在他家沙发上过夜
Won't let you spend the night on his couch.
你们对派对气球有何想法
Okay, so how do you feel about party balloons?
铝箔气球  可以
Uh, Mylar balloons, yes.
乳胶气球  拒绝
Latex balloons, no.
水球  我会上天台跳楼
Water balloons, I will jump off the roof
而且对准你的车跳
and aim for your car.
那音乐呢
All right, what about music?
我喜欢游行乐队
I enjoy marching bands
以及西藏喉音唱法
and Tibetan throat singing.
那就是不放音乐
No music it is.
你喜欢哪种蛋糕
What kind of cake do you like?
我的最爱是巧克力蛋糕搭配草莓糖霜
Well, my favorite is chocolate with strawberry frosting,
内含三层  如果要在上面题字
three layers, and if there's writing on it,
请确保别全都用大写
make sure it's not all caps.
我不想感觉我的蛋糕在吼我
I don't need my dessert yelling at me.
亚当·韦斯特在电话里听上去怎么样
Hey, so what was Adam West like on the phone?
挺友好的
Uh, nice guy.
但听到蝙蝠侠说出一些话  还是有点怪
But it was a little weird to hear Batman say,
他说"不要按门铃  我的贵宾犬会暴怒"
"Don't ring the doorbell or my poodles will go crazy."
你们知道亚当·韦斯特是我最喜欢的蝙蝠侠吗
You know, Adam West is my favorite Batman?
排在迈克尔·基顿
Well, after Michael Keaton,
克里斯汀·贝尔
Christian Bale
2005年《蝙蝠侠﹕侠影之谜》
2008年《蝙蝠侠：黑暗骑士》  2012年《黑暗骑士崛起》
以及《乐高大电影》里的蝙蝠侠之后
and Batman from The Lego Movie.
这种话你可别对他说
Don't say that to him.
干嘛  他可是排在乔治·克鲁尼前呢
What? He beat out George Clooney.
很了不起了好吗
And that's something.
也不想想我多爱克鲁尼啊
Like, I love me some Clooney.
这种话你可别对任何人说
Don't say that to anyone.
谢谢你来帮我们  斯图尔特
Thank you so much for helping us, Stuart.
我很庆幸你们能邀请我
Oh, I-I was just glad to be invited.
老实说  我一直觉得自己不属于你们的小团队
To be honest, I don't always feel like I'm part of the group.
亲爱的  我们赶时间
Okay, sweetie, we're on the clock here.
你能不能一边自怨自艾  一边抹糖霜呢
Can you hate yourself and frost at the same time?
希望我没来太早
Hello, I hope I'm not too early.
没有没有  快进来
No, no, no. Come on in.
容光焕发的准妈妈近来如何
And how is the radiant mommy-to-be?
非常棒
Doing great.
你怀孕了吗
Y-You're pregnant?
是的
Yeah.
听起来像是小团队成员之间该知道的事情
Sounds like something a member of the group might know.
是啊  生日派对优先办
Yeah, birthday party first.
自怜派对往后站
Pity party later.
你疯了吗
Are you crazy?
你怎么能把迈克尔·基顿
How can you put Michael Keaton
排在克里斯汀·贝尔之前呢
in front of Christian Bale?
得了吧
Oh, please.
就连我的贵宾犬都知道贝尔被高估了
Even my poodles know Bale's overrated.
谢谢
Thank you!
所以我觉得迈克尔·基顿排第一
That's why I say Keaton's number one.
他为这角色注入了一丝幽默感
He brought a sense of humor to the role.
如果你要连幽默感都考虑进去
Oh, if you're gonna factor in a sense of humor,
那我才应该排第一
then I should be at the top of the list.
排名应该是  我
It should be me,
基顿  基默
Keaton, Kilmer,
乐高蝙蝠侠  贝尔
Lego, Bale,
最后才是那个美男克鲁尼
and that pretty boy Clooney.
不是吧  你排在贝尔前面吗
Really? You're ahead of Bale?
这个男人可是这句话的化身啊
The man who personified the words,
我是蝙蝠侠
I'm Batman.
我从来不用说我是蝙蝠侠
I never had to say I'm Batman.
我一出现
I showed up.
人们就知道我是蝙蝠侠
People knew I was Batman.
所到之处  无论是上电视节目
Everywhere I went-- on the TV show,
参加商场开幕
mall openings...
甚至茱莉·纽玛家
Julie Newmar's bungalow.
我被说服了  你该排在贝尔前面
I'm sold-- you're ahead of Bale.
还有一个我排名应该更靠前的原因
There's another reason I should be higher on the list.
其他那些家伙
All those other guys
他们的戏服上还有假肌肉线条
had muscles built into their costumes.
而我的蝙蝠衣
All I had in my Batsuit
全靠爷的一级身材把肌肉线条撑出来
was 100%, grade-A West.
那我们都同意对阿弗莱克的演出有些发虚吗
Can we just all agree we're worried about Affleck?
-没错  -当然
- Sure. - Yeah, of course.
阿弗莱克是什么
What's an Affleck?
为什么我非得离开我自己的公寓
Is there a reason I had to leave my own apartment?
我觉得是他们想你看看
Well, I think they just want you to see it
公寓第一次被精心布置的样子
for the first time all decorated.
但我不在  谁来告诉他们做得不对呢
But who's gonna tell them they're doing it wrong?
我确信他们会让你发表感言
Well, I'm... I'm sure they'll ask you to give a speech,
到时候你再毒舌送他们上西天
and that's when you just tear 'em a new one.
不得不说
Have to say, you...
你穿这身西服看起来很帅
you do look good in that suit.
谢谢
Oh. Thank you.
或许晚点我会...
Maybe later I'll, uh...
有机会看你穿上生日装[裸体]
get to see you in your birthday suit.
但这就是我的生日服
But this is my birthday suit.
你是不是中风了
Are you having a stroke?
因为这种病会毁了生日派对的
Because that's the kind of thing that just ruins a birthday party.
妈妈  很惊讶你特意赶来
So, Mother, I'm surprised you came all this way
参加谢尔顿的生日
for Sheldon's birthday.
我很乐意这么做
Oh, I was happy to.
他也来参加我的60大寿了
He did come to my 60th.
你还搞了派对庆祝你60岁吗
Oh. You had a party for your 60th?
我不会称其为"派对"
Oh, I wouldn't call it a party.
就邀请了几个亲近的朋友
Just a few close friends.
还有你的兄弟姐妹
And your sister and brother.
公平来说  我们在赌城结婚
You know, to be fair, we did get married in Vegas
也没邀请她啊
and didn't invite her.
我还没有机会为此好好谢你呢  亲爱的
And I never did thank you for that, dear.
佩妮说大家都到了  你准备好了吗
Penny says everyone's there. Are you ready?
好了
I am.
等等  你还好吗
Wait. Are you all right?
不好  我有一点头晕
No, I just... I got a little light-headed.
你需要休息下吗
Oh, d-do you need a minute?
不用了
No.
如果我能从橱窗有鹦鹉的那个宠物店走过
No, if I can walk past that pet shop with the parrot in the window,
那我也能撑过这个
I suppose I can do this.
生日快乐
Happy birthday!
感言  感言
Speech! Speech!
来嘛  谢尔顿  说两句
Come on, Sheldon, say something.
非常感谢大家的到来
Uh, thank you all so much for coming.
贝弗莉
Uh, Beverly.
威尔·惠顿
Wil Wheaton.
不知道为啥  亚当·韦斯特也来了
Adam West, for some reason.
蝙蝠侠总算来参加你的生日派对了
Batman finally came to your party.
生日快乐  谢尔曼
Happy birthday, Sherman.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这一切真是太有心了
This is all so thoughtful.
抱歉
Excuse me.
你们还是会付我钱吧
I still get paid, don't I?
我看我还是进去和他好好谈一谈吧
Okay, I'd better go in there and talk to him.
你不觉得应该由我进去和他谈吗
Well, don't you think I'm the one who should go in?
无意冒犯  但我和他可是老交情了
No offense, but I've known the guy a really long time.
你知道  我曾经
Well, I've, you know,
见过他光屁股的样子
seen him without pants on.
再一次无意冒犯  但我也见过
Again, no offense, but so have I.
他还曾经见过我光屁股的样子
Well, he's seen me without pants on.
再一次无意冒犯...
Again, no...
你们俩够了
Okay, this is ridiculous.
谢尔顿
Sheldon?
我可以进来吗
Can I come in?
你怎么知道我不是在上厕所
How do you know I'm not using the facilities?
因为你每周都会把你的如厕时间表发给我
Because you e-mail me your bathroom schedule once a week,
尽管我点击退订这个周报
even though I've clicked unsubscribe,
快1000次了
like, a thousand times.
所以...
So...
你是怎么了
what's going on?
我不知道
I don't know.
我环顾四周
I-I looked around the room,
看到一张张笑脸和满屋的礼物
and I saw all the faces and the presents,
压力如排山倒海般袭来
and it... it was just too much.
我懂你的意思
I get that.
你想不想只叫几个人进来
Hey, you want to just bring a few people in here?
威尔·惠顿坐在浴缸里
You know, Wil Wheaton in the bathtub,
蝙蝠侠坐在马桶上
Batman on the toilet.
把这里打造成最诡异的漫画展
It'll be like the weirdest Comic-Con ever.
我知道你们费心安排了这一切
I know that you worked hard to put this together.
抱歉我破坏了一切
I'm sorry I'm ruining it.
你才没有破坏呢
Oh, pl... You're not ruining it.
拉杰本还准备在某个时刻让大家
Look, at some point, Raj will try to get everyone
一起跳滑步舞
to do the Electric Slide.
那才会毁掉一切呢
Now, that will ruin it.
我可能没法再回去客厅了
I don't think I can go back out there.
没关系
That's fine.
我很恨你妹妹和她的朋友
You know, I hate that your sister and her friends
曾经折磨过你
used to torture you.
但我更厌恶的是  如果那时候我在
But what I hate even more is, if I was there,
我可能也会一起折磨你
I would have tortured you, too.
从你的这加油打气来看  你还在折磨我呢
Based on this pep talk, I'd say you're still doing it.
我的意思是
My point is,
要是以前  我肯定不会
there was a time I never would've been friends
和你这样的人做朋友  但现在...
with someone like you, and now...
你成了我最喜欢的人之一
you are one of my favorite people.
所以  如果你希望
So, if what you need is
在厕所里过你的生日
to spend your birthday in a bathroom,
我也很愿意陪着你
I'm happy to do it with you.
大家肯定会觉得我是怪胎
Well, everyone will think I'm weird.
亲爱的  你的确很怪异
Sweetie, you are weird.
每个人都知道你是个异类
Everyone knows you're weird,
但他们今天齐聚一堂
but they're all still here
是因为他们发自内心地在乎你
because they care about you so much.
对不起
Hello.
有人需要进来打理一下发型
Some of us need to check our hair
因为可能有机会和莱纳德的妈妈"来一发"哦
because we might have a shot with Leonard's mother.
莱纳德
Leonard.
好久不见
It's been a while.
莱斯利
Leslie.
我都不记得上次聊天是什么时候的事了
I can't remember the last time we talked.
物是人非啊
So much has changed.
是吗
Has it?
是啊  佩妮和我结婚了
Yeah, uh, um, Penny and I got married.
恭喜你们
Wow, congratulations.
你知道吗
You know, actually,
我以为你这辈子都会和谢尔顿住在一起呢
I thought you'd be living with Sheldon forever.
这个嘛...
Yeah, well...
有空常联络
Don't be a stranger.
好了各位
Okay, everybody,
谢尔顿马上就要出来了
Sheldon is gonna come back out,
但他有点不好意思
but I think he's a little embarrassed,
所以大家一定要分外友善  好吗
so let's all be extra nice, okay?
你看着我干嘛
What are you looking at me for?
我就是个圣人好吗
I'm a saint.
但我也是床上小恶魔哟
But a sinner in the sack.
各位
Hello, everyone.
我...
I-I...
我要为自己的行为道歉
I'd like to apologize for my behavior.
希望我没有给大家派对的兴头泼冷水
I hope it hasn't put a damper on the party.
所以请大家尽情地玩吧
So, just, please, enjoy yourselves.
场面一下子就乱套了啊
Oh, this is quickly getting out of hand.
请允许我
If I may,
发表一下祝词
I-I'd like to propose a toast.
感谢各位今天的光临
Um, thank you all for coming tonight.
我知道通常都是由生日寿星
I know it's customary for the birthday boy
收取礼物
to receive presents,
但我觉得在寿星诞生的那一天
but I feel like I got the greatest gift
我得到了世界上最好的礼物
the day he was born.
-说得好  -谢谢
- Hear, hear. - Cheers.
艾米  你说得太好了
Amy, that was lovely.
这还挺好玩的
You know, this is fun.
我们应该继续
Let's do more.
谁快点再来称赞我两句
Someone else say something wonderful about me.
谢尔顿  我不觉得每个人...
Sheldon, I don't think everyone...
沃罗威茨  很好  大家听听他要说什么
Wolowitz, perfect. Everyone listen to Wolowitz.
好吧  那个
Okay, then, uh,
谢尔顿  我们已经认识很久了
Sheldon, we've known each other a long time.
跟你一起工作  成为朋友
And it is a pleasure to work with you
真是很愉快的一件事
and call you my friend.
有点普通  继续想  一会再轮到你
Little generic. Keep thinking. We'll circle back.
威尔·惠顿  你来
Wil Wheaton, go.
谢尔顿  我们的关系起起伏伏
Sheldon, I know that we've had our ups and downs,
但我能诚心地说  我的生活因为有你
but I can honestly say that my life is so much more interesting
变得更加精彩纷呈
because you are in it.
我们的相遇  也许缘于你是《星际迷航》粉丝
We may have met because you are a fan of Star Trek.
但我已经成为了你谢尔顿·库珀的粉丝
But I have become a fan of Sheldon Cooper.
繁荣昌盛  朋友
Live long and prosper, buddy.
生日快乐
And happy birthday.
干杯
Cheers.
跟人家学着点  沃罗威茨
That's how you do it, Wolowitz.
现在明白为什么人家能出名  你不行了吧
Now you see why he's famous and you're not.
谢尔顿
Sheldon,
我知道你的未来一片光明
I know the future holds great things for you,
我们对此迫不及待
and we all can't wait to see what they are.
生日快乐  亲爱的
Happy birthday, dear.
干杯
Cheers.
快给动物管理局打电话
Someone call Animal Control.
一条美丽的母豹[熟女]跑出来了
There's a cougar on the loose.
巴瑞  别这样
Barry, stop.
说真的  巴瑞  别这样
Seriously, Barry, stop.
甘地曾经说过
And it was Gandhi who said,
珍惜生活
live as if you were to
就象死神即将来临
die tomorrow.
热爱学习  就象生命能够永恒
Learn as if you were to live forever.
谢尔顿·库珀说  快点说
And it was Sheldon Cooper who said let's speed this up.
还有很多人等着致辞呢
A lot of people want to talk?
过去的我  也许会说点惹人嫌的话
Uh, in the past, I would've said something obnoxious,
比如  生日快乐啊  傻逼
like, happy birthday, dumbass?
但我现在不会了
But I'm not gonna do it.
你跟我都长大了
You and I have both grown a lot,
再见到你们  只有开心
and it's just so nice to see you all again.
所以
So
生日快乐  谢尔顿
happy birthday, Sheldon.
你知道我讨厌改变  说吧
Oh, now, you know I hate change. Say it.
生日快乐啊  傻逼
Happy birthday, dumbass!
生日快乐  年轻人
Happy birthday, young man.
如果你们有人很享受今日见到我
And if any of you have enjoyed seeing me here today,
我还承接动漫大会
I'm also available for Comic-Cons,
单身派对和成人礼...
bachelor parties, bar mitzvahs...
大家把我想说的都说了
I can't think of anything to say that hasn't already been said.
所以  敬你  谢尔顿
So, here's to you, Sheldon.
说得好
Hear, hear. Hear, hear.
谢谢你  伯纳黛特
Thank you, Bernadette.
说得真好
That was perfect.
什么  你逗我呢吧
What? You gotta be kidding me?
谢尔顿  我们在一起生活得太久了
Sheldon, we've been together so long,
久到我想不起来那些没有你的时光
it's hard to remember a time you weren't in my life.
相信我  我很努力想过了
And believe me, I try.
你让我开怀
You make me laugh.
让我在科学家的路上继续前行
You make me a better scientist.
还让我发疯
You make me crazy.
对我来说  你不仅仅是室友
You're more than just my roommate,
而是我的兄弟
you're my brother.
谢谢你
Thank you.
生日快乐  兄弟
Happy birthday, buddy.
干杯
Cheers.
谢谢你  说得太好了
Thank you. That-that was wonderful.
等等  等等
Oh, wait, wait, wait.
斯图尔特还没说呢
Stuart didn't get to speak.
好的  那个...
Oh, oh, okay. Um...
谢尔顿
Uh, Sheldon,
我大部分的人生  都活得像个隐形人
I've spent most of my life feeling invisible,
而有了你和大家...
but having you and everyone...
大家  注意一下
Hey, everybody, listen up.
表现不错
You nailed it.
这里有一位无法到场
We've got someone who couldn't be here
但很想对你说一声生日快乐的人
but really wanted to wish you a happy birthday.
你好  谢尔顿
Hello, Sheldon.
霍金教授
Professor Hawking.
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
不敢相信  你居然...
I can't believe you're...
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
你是在唱歌啊  抱歉
Oh, you're singing. Well, I'm sorry.
亲爱的谢尔顿生日快乐
Happy birthday, dear Sheldon.
霍金教授
Uh, Professor Hawking,
请等我们一下  马上去点蜡烛
if you just give us one second, we'll light the candles,
就可以一起唱了
and we can all sing together.
我唱得正爽呢  也行吧
I was crushing it, but all right.
好的  趁他们去拿蛋糕的时候
Okay, while they get the cake,
谢尔顿  我只想说
Sheldon, I just want to say,
别以为今晚你可以平安度过
I hope you didn't think you were gonna get through tonight
不用跟人拥抱哟
without a hug.
以前我是痛恨拥抱
You know, I used to hate these hugs.
现在只是超烦拥抱
Now they're just extremely irritating.
你可以起头了  霍金教授
Ready when you are, Professor Hawking.
一  二
And a one, and a two...
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you
亲爱的谢尔顿生日快乐
Happy birthday, dear Sheldon
-祝你生日快乐  -快乐
- Happy birthday to you. - ...to you.
行了  谁送我回家
So, who's taking me home?